Previously, we discussed 15 key architectural decisions that we need to build a production-ready
generative application. Now, the first one we discussed on a Gen A service, then we talked about
LLM selection, then the third one we deep dive into responsible AI and guardrails.
Now, the fourth important aspect is the prompt in January. Okay, let's quickly review few
key terms. So, first we have the foundation model and let's say we have the end user who provides
an input to this foundation model to generate a response. So, the prompt here refers to the
input provide to the foundation model to elicit a response. So, the response generated is
called as completion and the entire process where we send the prompt to the model and it generates
a response as inference or inferencing. Now, the quality of the prompts that you provide to
the foundation model can impact the quality of their response. So, there are multiple ways in which
you can improve the quality of the response from the foundation model. So, you have rag or retrieval
augmented generation, then your customization of foundation models using fine tuning and so on.
And we are going to discuss all of these in the later lectures, but the simplest and most cost
effective way to improve the quality of the response from the foundation models known as
prompt engineering. So, prompt engineering refers to the practice of optimizing textual
input to the foundation model to obtain desired response. Now, let's take a look at some of the
elements of a good prompt design. Now, here we have a long article related to football
and Lionel Messi. Let's say we send this to the foundation model with this comment summarize.
Now, our foundation model does not have any context on what is this article and if he has to
summarize in how many words does he need to summarize or what should be the output format.
So, the output that the foundation model is going to generate may not be so great. So, what are the
key elements of a good prompt design? So, the first one is you should provide some contextual
information about the task. So, here you can see now we have provided contextual information
we are saying this is the review of the football world cup from Qatar 2022.
The next we provide the input text for the task and then we clearly lay out the task specification.
In this case we are asking it to summarize this text. Then we are also telling it summarize the
above review in two lines. So, we are giving a clear output specification saying that summarize in
two lines. So, in summary if you have to get great output from the foundation model we should
give it clear and concise instructions define the task to be accomplished at the end and then
also give it the output specification. So, there are different prompt engine techniques
that can help you improve the desired outcome from the foundation model or the large
language model. So, here you can see we start with the baseline foundation model and then we use
zero short prompting and see if we get the desired outcome from the large language model.
So, if this does not work then we move to one short prompting and then few short prompting until
we achieve the perfect outcome. Now, there are two more techniques called as chain of thought
reasoning and re-act reasoning and action which we are going to discuss later in the section on
agents because both of these techniques are used in the agentic AI arena. So, let us start with
zero short prompting. Foundation models are capable of performing some simple tasks
zero short. So, what it means is no examples are needed to be provided to the foundation model
to accomplish the task. Let us say we give a prompt to the foundation model we are
saying write an engaging product description for a t-shirt for a clothing e-commerce site
and our foundation model goes ahead and writes the engaging description.
So, in one short prompting we provide an example to the model to assist the model to
comprehend and generate responses. Now, let us take a look at an example. So, this whole is our
prompt. So, first we give the model an example. Let us say write an engaging product description
for a clothing e-commerce site and then we tell it this is the product women's boho beach dress
and then we define some features here and then we tell the model how to write this description.
So, we give this example of the description. Then we tell model what it needs to do
in the same prompt. So, we tell it write an engaging description for the clothing e-commerce site.
Make sure to include following features in the description. So, we say product this time is humor,
men's graph t-shirt and the features are soft cotton, short, sleeve, have a print,
Einstein code and so on and then we leave this description blank. So, this time it will be able to
write the product description. So, this is the output it has generated by learning through an
example that we had given as part of the prompt. Now, there could be scenarios where the model
still cannot provide the write output even after giving one example.
Now, in future prompting you give few examples to the model to generate high quality output.
So, here is how we write the prompt. So, first we give an example of how to write an engaging
product description. So, we write we tell it about the product then give it the features
and then write the description. Then we give it another example write an engaging product
description. Then we give the second product we give features and write the description ourselves.
Then in the third case we give the product name humor, men's graph t-shirt, we give features
and then ask it to complete the description. And you can see this is the output it has generated.
So, in this scenario our foundation model understands through the multiple examples that we have
given to generate the write output. Now, in some scenarios even this might not work,
then we can look at the chain of thought reasoning, reasoning and action or react or if the
prompt engineering site does not work then we move on to retrieval augmented generation or model
customization. But prompt engineering is the most cost effective and easiest way to improve the
model output. So, that is pretty much it from this lecture I will see in the next lecture.
Thank you.